Ahmer Iqbal

ahmeriq09@hotmail.com

+91-7065005339

Noida, U. P

LinkedIn

SUMMARY

With three years' experience working as a data scientist and overall, ten years of strong professional background in analytical modeling and software engineering, I am a driving force determined to solve complex business problems using modern analytical models.

TOOLS & FRAMEWORKS

Language: Python, Java, R

Frameworks: TensorFlow, Transformers, Spacy, Keras, Pandas, scikit-learn, SciPy, imblearn, shell scripting, Ansible, NextJs

Tools: NLP, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, AWS, Google Cloud, Docker, Jenkins, Vector, Unix, Tableau, BigQuery,

Gemini api

WORK EXPERIENCE

Hewlett Packard Enterprise - Data Scientist/Lead Full Stack Developer

August 2023 – February 2024

Noida

Noida

- Implemented a 'health score' feature for in the product using machine learning model and custom datasets, created from GitHub metrics to evaluate Devops releases and their stability in Production. This feature resulted in a 15% increase in customer satisfaction.
- Developed and implemented data pipelines for real-time data processing of observability data from in-house IT systems. Live feeds for **three** production applications, all captured and refined for enhanced RCA capabilities.
- Led the development team in upgrading an in-house product, focusing on capturing metrics from Devops releases and leveraging NextJs framework. The upgrade decreased the build time of the application by 5% after commit.
- Development of informative visualizations on Tableau and integrating such dashboards on the in-house application. This visibility of this feature doubled the overall visibility of the application in the first month.

Ericsson India global Services Pvt LTD - Data Scientist

June 2021 – August 2023

- Holding 100% SLA deliveries as SPOC for four international clients and integral part of problem management teams, presenting
 analytical findings of their internal processes, fault/anomaly analysis of special use-cases to key stakeholders.
- Automated statistical analysis using ETL pipelines and Tableau dashboards, resulting in a 40% reduction in time spent on data analysis by internal teams.
- Management of large volumes of Telecommunication data including onboarding of new data and refinement of existing data sources through feature engineering and feature selection, used for creating analysis and multiple data science models.
- Optimized customer Fault work orders segmentation through text classification, resulting in operational efficiency up to 92%.
- Implemented frequent itemset using Apriori Algorithm of Alarms (Market Basket Analysis) for newly onboarded client which led to reduced analysis time by 62% while creating new operating rules for telecom alarm systems.

Tata Consultancy Services – Production Support Engineer/Devops

July 2011 – August 2019

Luxembourg/Gurgaon

- L3-support SPOC for Production and UAT applications deployed on client servers. Responsible for any user queries, production troubleshooting & fault replication concerning our application.
- Liaison with client- internal infra team for smooth transitioning of product releases throughout the year concerning functional and technical changes.
- Architect ansible/shell scripts for performance analysis and monitoring of production & development servers.
- Lead DevOps through hardware upgrades, batch processing and client-side environment setup.
- Spearheaded design and deployment of Release Management process using tools like Jenkins, Git to maintain continuous integration and automated release at offshore team.

INTERNSHIP & STARTUPS

IPSOS – Data Scientist Intern

November 2019 - March 2020 Paris

- Worked as Data Scientist in Social Intelligence and Analytics team; Text Classification (Binary/Multi class) of social media posts based on its relevance (Useful vs Ads)
- Sentiment Analysis of targeted brand posts by fine-tuning of BeRT and Camembert models which included comparing predictions obtained from these models with other python sentiment packages (VADER/Text Blob)
- Developed Production grade Topic Modelling Clustering Models used on corpus of country wise social media posts; This includes visualization of obtained topics, hashtags and mentions to analyze relations between clusters.

Foundercore - Cloud Engineer

August 2020 - April 2021

Gurgaon

- Worked as Director/Cloud Engineer understanding client requirements and R&D various LMS architecture and distributions in the market.
- Handling Client IT infrastructure & data migration from client's existing service provider to client AWS S3 buckets using Lambda including email migrations.
- Creating CI/CD pipelines using AWS code pipeline for UI development; Structuring in-house team management and new hiring of developers/freelancers; Configuring AWS CloudWatch on ec2 for monitoring useful metrics for debugging network outages.

EDUCATION

Data ScienceTech Institute - Applied MSC in Data Science & Al

March 2020 Paris/Nice

Sikkim Manipal Institute of Technology – Bachelor of Engineering

April 2011 Sikkim